M. Adil Yalçın

 www.adilyalcin.me
yalcin@umd.edu
2117 Hornbake Building, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742



Data ↔ Human Interface Designer

Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science University of Maryland, College Park

Lowering the barriers in rich visual & interactive data analysis for a broad audience

is the driving motivation of my work. I target challenges in design, development, engineering, and computation. Human Computer Interaction Lab (HCIL) is my current home for research.

Most of my solutions become part of Keshif (www.keshif.me), an out-of-the-box visual data exploration environment for the web.

To <u>work with me</u> to build next-gen data analytics solutions based on human-centered design and research, or for consulting, contact me at <u>valcin@umd.edu</u> or (linkedin.com/in/adilyalcin).

*I am a green card holder and do not need visa sponshorship.

Education



Ph.D. Candidate

Computer Science, University of Maryland, College Park, USA Thesis: Towards Rapid, Effective and Flexible Visual Data Exploration Advisors: Niklas Elmqvist, Ben Bederson

Sep. 2010 - Dec. 2016 (Expected)



Master of Science

Computer Engineering, Bilkent University, Ankara, Turkey Thesis: Real-Time Simulation and Visualization of Deformations on Heightfields Advisor: Bülent Özgüç, Co-Advisor: Tolga Çapın

June 2008

June 2010



Bachelor of Science

Computer Engineering, Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey Senior Project: Operational Simulation System - OPSIMUS

Skills

Goal

User Interfaces / Visualization / Front End / Design

Development

Data Processing / Back End

Computer Graphics, Simulation

Effective, simple solutions to complex challenges

JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3, d3, Photoshop

SublimeText, less, Version control (git/svn)

Node.is, SQL, Python, Java, Matlab

C++, C, OpenGL / GLSL, OpenCL / Cuda, Lua

Publications

AggreSet: Rich and Scalable Set Exploration using Visualizations of Element Aggregations

M. Adil Yalçın & Niklas Elmqvist & Ben Bederson

INFOVIS '15 - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. of the VAST / InfoVis / SciVis 2015)

Cognitive Stages in Visual Data Exploration

M. Adil Yalçın & Niklas Elmqvist & Ben Bederson

BELIV '16 - Proceedings of Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization at IEEE VIS 2016

Information Visualization

M. Adil Yalçın & Catherine Plaisant

Big Data and Social Sciences - CRC Publishing

PixelPie: Maximal Poisson-disk Sampling with Rasterization

Cheuk Yiu Ip & M. Adil Yalçın & David Luebke & Amitabh Varshney

HPG '13 - Proceedings of the 5th High-Performance Graphics Conference

GPU Algorithms for Diamond-based Multiresolution Terrain Processing

M. Adil Yalçın & Kenneth Weiss & Leila De Floriani

EGPGV '11 - Proceedings of the 11th Eurographics conference on Parallel Graphics and Visualization

Incorporating Learning Analytics into Basic Course Administration: How to Embrace the Opportunity to Identify Inconsistencies and Inform Responses

Lindsey B. Anderson & Elizabeth E. Gardner & Andrew D. Wolvin & Rowena Kirby-Straker & Adil Yalcin & Ben Bederson

NCA 2015 - 101th Annual meeting of the National Communication Association

Real-Time Simulation and Visualization of Deformations on Heightfields

M. Adil Yalcın

M.Sc. Thesis - Bilkent University

A Generic Multi-View Rendering Engine Architecture

M. Adil Yalçın & Tolga Çapın

Game Engine Gems Volume 2 - A.K. Peters

Route Visualization in Indoor Panoramic Imagery with Open Area Maps

Mateis Stroila & M.Adil Yalcin & Joe Mays & Narayanan Alwar

ICMEW '12 - IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo Workshops

Editing Heightfield using History Management and 3D Widgets

M. Adil Yalçın & Tolga Çapın

ISCIS '09 - 24th International Symposium on Computer and Information Sciences

Work Experience

START (National Consortium for the Study of Terrorism and Responses to Terrorism) - College Park, MD 2016 - now Research & Development ≯ Global Terrorism Database

SESYNC (National Socio-Environmental Synthesis Center) - Annapolis, MD

2015 - 2016

Research & Development > Data to Motivate Synthesis

Teaching and Learning Transformation Center, UMD - College Park, MD

2014 - 2015

Research & Development > Education Data Analysis

AT&T Labs Research - Florham Park, New Jersey

R&D Internship > Free viewpoint synthesis using depth and color sensors

2012 Summer

Projects and Tools

Keshif: Data Made Explorable

Leshif is a visual interactive data exploration enviroenment, built for the web, designed for expressiveness with minimalism.

MusicDigger

i MusicDigger is a tool that lets you "discover discographies" and "browse artist networks".

OpenRenderingEngine (OpenREng)

i A 3D rendering library that supports mobile and desktop GPUs on modern OpenGL.

Base Terrain Engine

1 Base Engine is built from various research projects on terrain meshes.

Parallel Region Quad-Tree Construction on GPUs

♣ A bottom-up approach to construct quadtrees from an arbitrary image or set of nodes.

Discrete Voronoi Diagrams using Programmable Graphics Hardware

implementation of a fast GPu algorithm to generate Voronoi Diagrams for 2D points.

Operation Simulations System (B.Sc. Senior Project)

i OPSIMUS is a simulation system in which the aim of the users is to complete an operational task.